<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Search><pages Count="63"><page Index="1"><![CDATA[Advance to Zero


    John F Hunt Ltd


































                                                                                                                                                          1]]></page><page Index="2"><![CDATA[Contents





                                                                                                                                 Introduction  3
                                                                                                                            Carbon Footprint   4
                                                                                                                                  Normative  6
                                                                                                                               Baseline data   7
                                                                                                                               Commitments  9
                                                                                                                            Our commitment  10
                                                                                                                              Key Legislation  10
                                                                                                                           Carbon Hierarchy  11
                                                                                                                             Waste Hierarchy   12
                                                                                                                 Embodied Carbon Baselines   13
                                                                                                                       Material Reuse Targets   15
                                                                                                                               Reuse Options   16
                                                                                                                     Circular Economy Guide   17
                                                                                                                                   Concrete  18
                                                                                                                                        Steel  23
                                                                                                                                       Bricks  28
                                                                                                                                      Timber  32
                                                                                                                                       Glass  37
                                                                                                                         Furniture & Materials   41
                                                                                                                                        Fuels  46
                                                                                                                 Circular Economy Database  51
                                                                                                               Low Carbon Supplier Database  54
                                                                                           Environmental Product Declaration (EPD) Database  55
                                                                                                                                  Innovation  57







                                                                                                                                                          2]]></page><page Index="3"><![CDATA[Introduction





               The primary driver of climate change is the excessive emission of greenhouse gases (GHGs) into the atmosphere, primarily carbon dioxide (CO2)
               from burning fossil fuels such as coal, oil, and natural gas. These emissions trap heat in the Earth's atmosphere, leading to the greenhouse effect
               and subsequent warming of the planet.

               Construction activities in the UK have a notable impact on climate change due to their energy consumption, greenhouse gas emissions, and
               resource depletion. Here are some key aspects to consider:

                   •   Greenhouse Gas Emissions: Construction activities contribute to greenhouse gas emissions through several stages, including
                       manufacturing materials, transportation, on-site energy use, and waste management. Cement production, a crucial component of
                       construction, is particularly carbon-intensive, releasing significant amounts of CO2 during the manufacturing process. Construction
                       machinery, such as excavators and trucks, also contribute to emissions.

                   •   Energy Consumption: Construction projects require substantial energy for heating, cooling, and powering equipment on-site. The energy
                       sources used can vary, with fossil fuels being a common choice. The energy consumption during the construction phase adds to the
                       overall carbon footprint of the built environment.

                   •   Material Sourcing and Waste: Construction activities require vast amounts of raw materials, such as concrete, steel, and timber.
                       Extracting, processing, and transporting these materials contribute to energy consumption and emissions. Additionally, construction
                       generates substantial waste, including construction debris and discarded materials. Proper waste management practices, including
                       recycling and reuse, can minimise the environmental impact.

                   •   Policy and Regulation: The UK government has implemented policies and regulations to address climate change impacts in the
                       construction sector. Building regulations enforce minimum energy performance standards, and initiatives like the Green Homes Grant
                       scheme aim to improve energy efficiency in existing buildings. The Construction Industry Strategy 2025 also focuses on reducing carbon
                       emissions and promoting sustainable construction practices.

                   •   Circular Economy and Low Carbon Materials: Moving towards a circular economy model can significantly reduce the environmental

                                                                                                                                                          3]]></page><page Index="4"><![CDATA[impact of construction. This involves using recycled or reclaimed materials, adopting prefabrication techniques, and designing for
                       deconstruction and material reuse. The development and use of low carbon or carbon-neutral materials, such as sustainable timber and
                       low-carbon cement alternatives, also play a vital role in mitigating climate change.





















































                                                                                                                                                          4]]></page><page Index="5"><![CDATA[Carbon Footprint



    John F Hunt































                                                                                                                                                          5]]></page><page Index="6"><![CDATA[Carbon Footprint




               A company's carbon footprint refers to the total greenhouse gas (GHG) emissions directly and indirectly produced by its operations, products,
               and services over a specific period, typically measured in metric tons of carbon dioxide equivalent (CO2e). It encompasses the emissions
               associated with the company's energy consumption, transportation, waste management, and other activities throughout its value chain.

               The carbon footprint of a company can be categorized into three scopes, known as the "Scope 1, 2, and 3" emissions:

                   •   Scope 1 Emissions: These emissions are direct emissions produced by the company's own activities. They include emissions from on-site
                       combustion of fossil fuels, such as natural gas used for heating or fuel for company-owned vehicles. Scope 1 emissions are considered
                       direct because they originate from sources owned or controlled by the company.

                   •   Scope 2 Emissions: Scope 2 emissions are indirect emissions associated with the generation of purchased electricity, heat, or steam
                       consumed by the company. These emissions result from the combustion of fossil fuels at power plants or other energy generation sources
                       that supply the company with electricity. Although the emissions occur off-site, they are attributed to the company's activities.

                   •   Scope 3 Emissions: Scope 3 emissions are indirect emissions that occur throughout the company's value chain, including both upstream
                       and downstream activities. These emissions are often the most significant portion of a company's carbon footprint and encompass a
                       wide range of activities, such as emissions from purchased goods and services, transportation and distribution, employee commuting,
                       business travel, and the use and disposal of sold products.

               Calculating and reporting a company's carbon footprint involves collecting data on energy consumption, fuel usage, transportation, waste
               generation, and other relevant activities. These data are then converted into CO2e emissions using emission factors specific to each emission
               source. Many organizations use recognised international standards and protocols, such as the Greenhouse Gas Protocol, to ensure consistency
               and accuracy in their carbon footprint calculations.

               Carbon emissions are significant due to their central role in climate change and the resulting environmental, social, and economic
               consequences. Addressing carbon emissions is crucial for mitigating climate change, protecting the environment, safeguarding human health,
               and fostering a sustainable and resilient future.



                                                                                                                                                          6]]></page><page Index="7"><![CDATA[Normative


               Normative is an advanced carbon accounting engine which provides 100% coverage across scopes 1, 2 and 3, as well as high-resolution
               insights to help us identify actionable emissions reductions.

                       Collection   Description                     Data Source      Assumptions Made
                       Boundary
                       Mobile       Fuel used by vehicles the company  Fuel card     Data taken from Fuel Cards used in company vehicles. The fuel used is broken
                       Combustion   owns or controls.               records.         down and attributed to JFH Group Companies according to their vehicle
                                                                                     ownership, JFH Ltd. Equates to 7.86% of Company Vehicle Fuel consumption.
                Scope   Stationary   Fuel used by machinery or      Fuel records on   The time period across which the fuel is used is assumed to be from the date the
                   1    Combustion   equipment the business owns or   Import/Export logs.  fuel was delivered to site to the date of the subsequent fuel delivery (or if there
                                    controls.                                        was none the project end date).

                       Electricity    Electricity purchased by the   Monthly office   Where the electricity usage on the bill applies to offices owned by other
                                    companies’ various locations.    electricity bills.    businesses, JFHs usage is taken to be proportional to the share of the bill paid by
                                                                                     JFH.
                       Heating      Heating purchase by the         Monthly office gas  Where the gas usage on the bill applies to offices owned by other businesses, JFHs
                Scope               companies’ locations (excluding   bills.         usage is taken to be proportional to the share of the bill paid by JFH.
                   2                on-site equipment which is
                                    recorded in Scope 1).
                       Waste        How waste from production and   Waste removals   If the weight of the waste is not provided by the waste carrier or an on-site
                       generated in  other operations is treated.    recorded in the   weighbridge, the weight is estimated from the waste type and skip/container size
                       operations                                   site Import/Export  using the assumptions in the table below.
                                                                    logs.
                       Purchased    Day-to-day purchases made across Material delivery   If the weight of the material is not provided, it is either calculated from the volume
                       goods and    the company. Water usage falls   and water usage  (multiplied by the material density) or, if the volume is not provided, estimated
                       services     within this category.           recorded in the   using the same method as for waste outlined above.
                                                                    site Import/Export
                                                                    logs.
                       Upstream     Transport purchased by the      Waste removals   The distance travelled for each material delivery or waste removal is calculated
                       transport and  company to move goods to/from   and material   from the depot/waste facility to the site and back using google maps.
                       distribution    our facilities.              deliveries recorded It is assumed that all material deliveries and waste removals are an HGV carrying
                                                                    in the site Import/  the weight of materials/waste specified.
                Scope                                               Export logs.
                   3    Employee    How our employees commute to    Causeway         For each record of an employee entering or leaving site, it is assumed that they
                       commuting   work, or work from home.         Donseed reports.   have travelled from/ are travelling to the home address they have provided using
                                                                                     the mode of transport they have given.



                                                                                                                                                          7]]></page><page Index="8"><![CDATA[Baseline Data


    2020/2021




























                                                                                                                                                          8]]></page><page Index="9"><![CDATA[Baseline Data 2020/21




               John F Hunt Ltd’s total baseline emissions (Scope 1,2 and 3) are 8997.1t for the period of May 2020 to May 2021 and are detailed below:













































                                                                                                                                                          9]]></page><page Index="10"><![CDATA[Our scope 3 emissions are largely made up of purchased goods and the embodied carbon that is related to the production and transportation
               of those products.

               Scope 3 emissions are considered challenging to address and account for because they often involve multiple factors and are influenced by
               various external factors beyond our direct control. However, in order to influence these areas best, we can stipulate lower embodied carbon
               products from suppliers and assess the EPD (Environmental Product Declaration) so that decisions are made both on price and carbon content.












































                                                                                                                                                         10]]></page><page Index="11"><![CDATA[Commitments



    Targets






























                                                                                                                                                         11]]></page><page Index="12"><![CDATA[Commitments





               John F Hunt Ltd will help mitigate climate change though the use of sustainable plant, fuel and machinery which includes company cars.
               However, we recognise that our own energy use contributes to climate change and is a significant operating cost to our business.

               Our Commitment

               As part of our ambitions to become carbon neutral, we have set the below minimum targets, which will assist in achieving the UK’s Net Zero
               targets:

                   •   Halve our greenhouse gas emissions before 2030

                   •   Achieve net zero emissions before 2050
                   •   Disclose our progress on a yearly basis

               Key Legislation

               Key UK carbon legislation measures that were in place as of September 2021:
                   1.  Climate Change Act 2008: This landmark legislation set legally binding targets for reducing greenhouse gas emissions in the UK. It

                       included a long-term goal of reducing emissions by at least 80% below 1990 levels by 2050.
                   2.  The Carbon Budgets: Under the Climate Change Act, the UK government set legally binding carbon budgets, which are five-year caps
                       on the total amount of greenhouse gases the UK can emit. These budgets were designed to provide a clear trajectory toward meeting
                       the long-term emission reduction targets.

                   3.  Net Zero by 2050: In June 2019, the UK government amended the Climate Change Act to include a legally binding target of reaching
                       net-zero greenhouse gas emissions by 2050. This means any remaining emissions would need to be balanced by removing an equivalent
                       amount of carbon from the atmosphere.


                                                                                                                                                         12]]></page><page Index="13"><![CDATA[Carbon Hierarchy



               The carbon reduction hierarchy, also known as the "hierarchy of carbon reduction" or "carbon mitigation hierarchy," is a framework used to
               prioritize strategies for reducing greenhouse gas emissions, particularly carbon dioxide (CO2) emissions. It provides a structured approach to
               address climate change by identifying and implementing measures to reduce carbon emissions in an efficient and effective manner.

               The hierarchy typically consists of the following steps, listed in order of priority:


                                                                                          Avoid:     Project planning to avoid carbon intensive
                                                                                                     construction. This is often referred to as “use less” and
                                           Avoid                                                     should be assessed during all aspects of our projects.
                                                                                                     This can either be through using fewer materials for the
                                                                                                     same output or reducing consumption of energy on
                                                                                                     site e.g. fuel or electricity.

                                          Reduce                                       Reduce:       Look to reduce consumption through usitlising local
                                                                                                     procurement, low carbon travel initiatives and an
                                                                                                     increase in efficiency of the energy already
                                                                                                     consumed. This can include hybrid machinery,
                                                                                                     generator sets partnered with flybrid components.

                                           Replace                                    Replace:         The replacement of high energy intensity products
                                                                                                     with low carbon alternatives. Example of this may be
                                                                                                     using HVO, low carbon cement or utilising recycled
                                                                                                     rebar within construction.

                                              Offset

                                                                                          Offset:    Offset the remaining emissions that cannot be
                                                                                                     managed out through the above practices.



                                                                                                                                                         13]]></page><page Index="14"><![CDATA[Waste Hierarchy



               The waste hierarchy emphasizes the importance of reducing waste generation and promoting recycling and resource recovery over disposal
               methods. It is designed to guide waste management practices and policies, with the ultimate goal of minimizing the environmental impact of
               waste.


                                                                                              Prevent:     Using less material in design and manufacture.
                                                                                                           Keeping products for longer; re use. Using less
                                    Prevention                                                             hazardous materials.  In the majority of cases, waste
                                                                                                           prevention is focused on materials, products and
                                                                                                           components before (somewhat confusingly) they
                                                                                                           become waste.
                                         Re-use                                               Re-use:      Reuse is any operation by which products or
                                                                                                           components that are not waste are used again for the
                                                                                                           same purpose. Examples include reclaimed bricks, the
                                                                                                           reuse of steel beams and reusable packaging systems.

                                         Recycle                                             Recycle:      There are two types of recycling:
                                                                                                           Closed loop - where the waste materials are recycled
                                                                                                           back into the same or a similar product.
                                                                                                           Open loop recycling - where the waste material is
                                                                                                           recycled back into different products
                                          Recovery                                         Recovery:       Recovery activities are incineration with energy
                                                                                                           recovery, gasification and pyrolysis (used for organic
                                                                                                           waste) which produce energy and anaerobic
                                                                                                           digestion and composting (also used for organic
                                                                                                           waste).

                                              Landfill                                        Landfill:    The landfilling of waste and the incineration of waste
                                                                                                           where energy is not recovered are disposal activities.
                                                                                                           In some cases, it may be necessary to landfill waste
                                                                                                           e.g. hazardous waste such as asbestos.



                                                                                                                                                         14]]></page><page Index="15"><![CDATA[Embodied Carbon Baselines




                      CLF Materials Baseline Report 2021                  2021 CLF BASELINES v2
                                                                        kg CO2e per declared unit

                                                                   Achievable   Typical   Baseline                     Achievable   Typical   Baseline
                 Category                          Subtype         (Low)      (Median)   (High)     unit      Method   (Low)      (Median)   (High)   unit
                 CONCRETE
                 Ready Mixed Concrete              0-2500 psi (0-17.2
                                                   Mpa)               190        266        340     m3              1     475        665      850     Tonnes
                                                   2501-3000 psi
                                                   (17.2-20.7 MPa)    210        291        380     m3              1     525        728      950     Tonnes
                                                   3001-4000 psi
                                                   (20.7-27.6 MPa)    260        343        470     m3              1     650        858      1175    Tonnes
                                                   4001-5000 psi
                                                   (27.6-34.5 MPa)    320        406        580     m3              1     800       1015      1450    Tonnes
                                                   5001-6000 psi
                                                   (34.5-41.4 MPa)    330        429        610     m3              1     825       1073      1525    Tonnes
                                                   6001-8000 psi
                                                   (41.3-55.1 MPa)    380        498        710     m3              1     950       1245      1775    Tonnes
                                                   >8001 psi (>55.1
                                                   MPa)               411        535        710     m3              1     1028      1338      1775    Tonnes
                 Slurry                            Flowable Fill      90         170        230     m3              2     225        425      575     Tonnes
                                                   Structural Grout   270        458        620     m3              2     675       1145      1550    Tonnes
                                                                    Match ready mixed concrete values                     Match ready mixed concrete
                 Shotcrete                                                       per                m3              4            values per           Tonnes
                 MASONRY
                 Concrete Masonry Unit                                TBD        370        545     m3              2     TBD        925      1363    Tonnes
                 STEEL
                 Rebar                                                0.8        0.98       1.7     Tonnes          2     800        980      1700    Kg
                 Steel Wire and Mesh                                       Match rebar values       Tonnes          4         Match rebar values      Kg
                 Plate Steel                                          1.0        1.47       3.0     Tonnes          3    1000.0     1470.0   3000.0   Kg

                 Structural Steel                  Hollow Sections    1.5        2.39       3.0     Tonnes          3    1500.0     2390.0   3000.0   Kg


                                                                                                                                                         15]]></page><page Index="16"><![CDATA[CLF Materials Baseline Report 2021                  2021 CLF BASELINES v2
                                                                        kg CO2e per declared unit

                                                                   Achievable   Typical   Baseline                     Achievable   Typical   Baseline
                 Category                          Subtype           (Low)     (Median)    (High)   unit       Method     (Low)   (Median)   (High)   unit
                                                   Hot-Rolled
                 Structural Steel                  Sections           0.8        1.16       1.7     Tonnes          2     800.0     1160.0   1700.0   Kg
                 Steel decking                                        1.5        2.37       3.1     Tonnes          3    1500.0     2370.0   3100.0   Kg
                 Cold Formed Steel                 Framing            1.5        2.28       3.0     Tonnes          3    1500.0     2280.0   3000.0   Kg
                                                   Open-web steel
                 Open-web steel joists             joists             0.7        1.38       2.5     Tonnes          3     700.0     1380.0   2500.0   Kg
                 ALUMINUM
                 Aluminum Extrusions                                  TBD        8.91       12.4    Tonnes          3     TBD       8910     12400    Kg
                 Thermally Improved Aluminum Extrusions               TBD        9.78       13.6    Tonnes          3     TBD       9780     13600    Kg
                 WOOD & COMPOSITES
                 Dimension Lumber                  Wood framing       50         63         100     m3              3     TBD        TBD      TBD     m3
                 Plywood & OSB Sheathing                              200        230        400     m3              2     TBD        TBD      TBD     m3
                 Glass Mat Gypsum Sheathing        1/2" (12.7 mm)     TBD        4.71       6.3     m2              3     TBD        TBD      TBD     m2
                 Glass Mat Gypsum Sheathing        5/8" (15.9 mm)     TBD        5.42       7.2     m2              3     TBD        TBD      TBD     m2
                 Prefabricated Wood Products       Wood I-joists      1.0        1.97       6.0     m               3     TBD        TBD      TBD     m
                 Composite Lumber                  LSL/LVL/PSL        230        361        400     m3              3     TBD        TBD      TBD     m3
                 Mass Timber                       GLT/CLT/DLT/NLT    104        137        200     m3              3     TBD        TBD      TBD     m3



















                                                                                                                                                         16]]></page><page Index="17"><![CDATA[Material Reuse Targets




                                                                           MATERIAL REUSE TARGET %
                 Material            2023            2024            2025            2026           2027            2028            2029            2030
                 Concrete             25              35              50             75              100             100             100            100

                 Glass                20              60              70             80              90              100             100            100
                 (Internal
                 Partitions)
                 Glass                0               10              25             25              25              25              25              25
                 Windows
                 Glass                0               10              25             25              25              25              25              25
                 External
                 Second Layer
                 Aluminium            0               5               10             15              20              20              20              20
                 Façade
                 Steel Frame          5               10              15             20              25              25              25              25
                 Steel Rebar          0               0               0               0               0               0               0              0

                 Ceiling Tiles        0               5               10             15              20              25              25              25
                 RAF                  50              75             100             100             100             100             100            100

                 Carpet Tiles         50              55              60             65              70              75              80              85
                 Stone                10              10              15             20              25              30              35              40
                 Cladding
                 Bricks               10              15              20             25              30              35              40              45

                 Timber               5               10              15             20              25              35              45              55

                 Ceramic              5               10              15             20              25              35              45              60




                                                                                                                                                         17]]></page><page Index="18"><![CDATA[Reuse Options






                                      Concrete and            Metal               Wood                Glass              Plastic            Insulation
                                     other stony waste

                                                        (i) steel-section   dimensional
                                    prefabricated
                                    concrete products   element could be  timbers,              glass panes and    plastic pipes and   insulation layer in
                                                                            chipboards,
                                                        reused;
                                    and elements
                Preparing for reuse                     (ii) whole portal   timber doors,       panels could be    claddings could     building elements
                                    (walls, floors, stairs,   frame buildings   windows, and    reused             be reused           could be reused
                                    floors, etc.) may   can be reclaimed  floorboards could
                                    be reused
                                                        for reuse           be reused
                                    processed as        re-melted to        recycled as         recycled as        processed as a      recycled for
                                    feedstock in new                                                               feedstock for
                Recycling                               produce new         feedstock in new    feedstock for new                      producing new
                                    concrete            ferrous products    wooden products  vitreous products     producing new       insulation
                                    production                                                                     plastic products

                                                                            (i) energy          (i) crushed for                        (i) energy
                                                                            recovery;           backfilling;
                                    downcycled for                          (ii) chipped as an   (ii) ground and                       recovery
                                    other applications  No recovery                                                                    (ii) processed as
                Other recovery                                              organic mulch in    refined as         energy recovery
                                    instead of making  options for steel.   gardening,          feedstock for                          additives for
                                    new concrete                                                                                       producing
                                                                            landscaping,        making concrete
                                                                            (iii) compost       and aerogel                            concrete
                                    should always be    should never be     should always be    should always be   should not be       should always be
                Disposal
                                    avoided             considered          avoided             avoided            considered          avoided









                                                                                                                                                         18]]></page><page Index="19"><![CDATA[Circular Economy Guide



               The circular economy is an alternative economic model that aims to decouple economic growth from resource consumption and
               environmental degradation. It is a systemic approach that seeks to redefine how we produce, consume, and dispose of goods and services. In
               contrast to the traditional linear economy, which follows a "take-make-dispose" model, the circular economy focuses on creating a closed-loop
               system where resources are kept in use for as long as possible, their value is maximized, and waste is minimized.





























               The key principles of the circular economy include:

                   •   Designing out Waste and Pollution: Products are designed to be durable, repairable, and recyclable. The focus is on eliminating waste
                       and pollution at the design stage by considering the entire lifecycle of a product.



                                                                                                                                                         19]]></page><page Index="20"><![CDATA[•   Keeping Products and Materials in Use: The circular economy emphasizes extending the life of products through repair, refurbishment,
                       and remanufacturing. It encourages sharing, leasing, and product-as-a-service models to maximize utilization and minimize the need for
                       new production.

                   •   Regenerating Natural Systems: The circular economy aims to restore and regenerate natural systems by promoting sustainable practices,
                       such as regenerative agriculture, reforestation, and ecosystem restoration. It seeks to minimize the extraction of virgin resources and
                       prioritize the use of renewable resources.

                   •   Closing the Loop on Materials: Emphasis is placed on recycling, reusing, and recovering materials from products at the end of their life.
                       This involves implementing effective waste management systems, promoting recycling infrastructure, and developing innovative
                       technologies for material recovery.






































                                                                                                                                                         20]]></page><page Index="21"><![CDATA[Circular Economy Guide



    Concrete

























                                                                                                                                                         21]]></page><page Index="22"><![CDATA[Concrete





                   Material Summary
                   Concrete within existing buildings is usually found on raft slabs, floor slabs and reinforcement throughout the building
                   structure. This provides John F Hunt with an opportunity for recycling and reuse through pile mat creation and other
                   applications.

                   Construction activities require concrete to be poured for reinforcement, the material traditionally has large amounts of

                   embodied carbon within it. By using replacement products, such as GGBS content, we can drive down the embodied
                   carbon and therefore our own emissions.




                 Most of the structural concrete and blockwork is unsuitable for reuse, as they are not in precast sections, and the
                 blockwork is unlikely to be able to be separated without significant damage.

                 Concrete is in theory 100% recyclable. It can be segregated and crushed for reuse as hard core, fill or in landscaping

                 or used as recycled aggregate in new concrete. Although recycled and secondary aggregates can be used in
                 some concrete applications, other lower grade end uses (e.g. in unbound materials as fill and hardcore) may
                 sometimes be more resource efficient due to reduced processing demands and transportation.

                 Often such waste does not even leave the demolition site, being used for the site’s redevelopment, as shown by the

                 NFDC figures with nearly half of inert waste (over 9 million tonnes) treated this way. Otherwise, it is used on other sites
                 as fill to offset the need for primary raw materials. Very little concrete waste therefore tends to go to landfill.
                 All waste management routes will be investigated and the most efficient and least carbon intensive route will be
                 chosen for every material leaving site.



                  Potential Waste Management Routes



                  Option 1 – Material removed from structure and then recycled off site.

                  Option 2 – Material crushed on site and then removed by waste carrier.
                  Option 3 – Material crushed on site and then reused in the redevelopment.                                                              22]]></page><page Index="23"><![CDATA[Concrete – John F Hunt Case Studies




              Low Carbon Concrete and EFC                                                                  Case Study: St Pancras Campus


              Currently global cement production accounts for an estimated 8% of         •   Through programming and agile works planning, the site team at St Pancras Campus have
              anthropogenic carbon dioxide (CO2) emissions worldwide1. After coal powered    managed to reduce the embodied carbon of the concrete package by 107 tCo2e, a 48.1%
              energy production, cement manufacturing is the next biggest global contributor in   reduction from the contracted specification.
              greenhouse gases. With the UK Governments pledge to achieve net zero by 20502   •   This is the equivalent to 65 return flights from London to New York - data from here -
              it is imperative to look into more environmentally friendly methods of work and   (https://calculator.carbonfootprint.com/calculator.aspx?lang=en-GB&tab=3)
              material procurement.                                                      •   The site team have applied John F Hunts new bespoke “Concrete Planning Tool” to make
                                                                                             concrete mix decisions based on the programme, environmental and logistical factors to
                                                                                             apply a hierarchy of design to ensure we are using the maximum amount of GGBS that the
                                                                                             project allows.
              The main issue with concrete production in terms of greenhouse gas emissions is   •   This planning tool has allowed John F Hunt to take advantage of the recent warm weather to
              that on average 1 tonne of concrete produced also produces 1 tonne of CO2e.    offset longer curing time of higher GGBS content to bring it within a working time frame,
              Concrete production contributes to CO2 emissions in a variety of ways, quarrying   achieving both a reduction in tCo2e but also remaining on programme.
              and transport account for less than 10% of concrete gas emissions, whereas clinker   •   In addition to this, they have been able to alter mix design within certain elements that allow
              production (process and thermal emissions) accounts for over 70% of all emissions   for a longer curing time to reach the desired strength, all of which allowing the success of the
              from concrete production1. All of which poses a huge question to the construction   project.
              industry, how can we supply our construction needs whilst also reducing our
              carbon footprint?



              The Chatham House report published in 2018 suggests a number of ways the
              construction industry could reduce concrete production emissions such as carbon
              capture, energy efficiency and clinker substitution1. The report states that the
              biggest reduction in emissions could be caused by ‘Novel Cements’. One of these
              such ‘Novel Cements’ is EFC® (Earth Friendly Cement®) has a view of reducing
              carbon emissions whilst ultimately aiming to replace CEM I.



              John F Hunt is committed to reducing its Carbon Footprint in all aspects of our
              activities, with the use of EFC® being one way in which we can achieve this. EFC®
              has been chosen as a potential material due to the large number of Third-Party
              trials and data supplied by external suppliers. GGBS levels within the concrete,
              using fly ash, reduces the embodied carbon within the product.

                                                                                                                                                         23]]></page><page Index="24"><![CDATA[Concrete Procurement Procedure






















































                                                                                                                                                         24]]></page><page Index="25"><![CDATA[Concrete Waste Procedure





















































                                                                                                                                                         25]]></page><page Index="26"><![CDATA[Circular Economy Guide


    Steel























                                                                                                                                                         26]]></page><page Index="27"><![CDATA[Steel





                  Material Summary
                  Manufacturing of Steel is one of the most carbon intensive processes on the planet, therefore it is imperative that solutions are
                  explored for reuse and low carbon manufacturing.  John F Hunt is in prime position to dictate sustainable steel options through

                  removal of steel in demolition and civil work packages. This enables options from steel reuse to low carbon products to be identified
                  during the design stages. Future developments will strive to reduce the embodied carbon within manufactured steel, but currently
                  the best method is reusing structural steel in new developments through reuse partners and clients.



                 Steel has multiple waste management routes it can go down when being removed from an existing development.

                    In theory Steel is 100% recyclable and can be used again in structures if it is examined and is to an acceptable strength.

                 Traditionally Steel is taken from demolition projects and then melted down and recycled into new steel products. The excess
                 steel scrap is then melted down by a furnace that runs at a temperature of nearly 3,000 degrees, and purified to rid the scrap
                 of any contaminants. Then, the melted steel is solidified into sheets and prepped for shipping.
                 There are options now to Reuse Steel whether that be through Steel reclamation companies or through actual Reuse on the
                 redevelopment itself.

                 All steel being Reused will need to be graded and certified before any permanent works can be carried out.

                 Manufactured steel using different production methods, such as Electric Arc Furnaces using renewable energy, could also be
                 utilised in future.



                   Potential Waste Management Routes



                   Option 1 – Material removed from structure and then recycled off site.
                   Option 2 – Invite a Steel Reclamation Company such as Cleveland Steel to collect from John F Hunt
                   Option 3 – ReUse within new development

                                                                                                                                                         27]]></page><page Index="28"><![CDATA[Steel – John F Hunt Case Studies




                        Steel Reuse – 1 Exchange Square


              Through discussions with Cleveland Steel and Heyne Tillett Steel the opportunity to salvage
              and reuse steel from 175 Bishopsgate within the 1 Exchange development works. This

              collaboration allowed us to work on an innovative framework to reduce the project's
              embodied carbon through circular design strategies.

              Repurposing structural steel delivers significant environmental benefits, reducing the overall
              embodied carbon of your development by approximately 150t CO2e. The process involves:

                  •   Undertaking a site audit to identify material sizes and quantities and classify each
                      steel member into like groups, i.e. columns or rafters from like spans,
                  •   Careful deconstruction of steel using suitable identification methods to segregate
                      the material,
                  •   Steel is transported to Cleveland Steel and weighed,
                  •   Each piece is given a unique identification number and booked into an inventory.
                      This shows useable length, coatings, and any out-of-tolerance defects noted,
                  •   Each piece is annotated as to whether it has holes or attachments etc. Then it is   Xcarb Low Carbon Steel – Fenchurch Street
                      rated from 1 to 5 depending on the extent,
                  •   The material is then stored until it is required,                     Our 50 Fenchurch Street project purchased XCarb steel, supplied by ArcellorMittal. This

                  •   In preparation for reuse, Cleveland Steel will cut back any raggy ends, remove   product is a low carbon steel which focuses on Carbon reduction within the
                      coatings, remove attachments, and repair holes where and when required. This will
                      be in line with the component drawings at this stage to match inventory to its   production of the steel itself. Through focussing on steel production using renewable
                      specific future application,                                          energy and recycled steel content they have brought the embodied carbon of the

                  •   They then cut a 200 x 200mm test coop and send it to an independent laboratory   product down to 532 Co2e(Kg) per tonne. The Fenchurch Street project purchased 10
                      to verify and grade. The material can then be included in CE-marked structures.   tonnes of this product with a carbon cost of 5.32 Co2e(T). This is saving of 10.18 tonnes
                                                                                            of Co2 compared to traditional engineering steel production.


                 Route to Net Zero Steel on Projects:

                    •   Correct Steel Identification in Design Stage
                    •   Use Low Carbon Steel where structurally acceptable
                    •   Engage with supply chain to reduce travel and new traditional

                        steel production


                                                                                                                                                         28]]></page><page Index="29"><![CDATA[Steel Procurement Procedure






















































                                                                                                                                                         29]]></page><page Index="30"><![CDATA[Steel Waste Procedure























































                                                                                                                                                         30]]></page><page Index="31"><![CDATA[Circular Economy Guide


    Bricks























                                                                                                                                                         31]]></page><page Index="32"><![CDATA[Bricks





                   Material Summary
                  Bricks are everywhere and in a certain age of building they can make up a large percentage of waste material, yet often they
                  are taken for granted and their true potential is not realised. This can be down to a number of factors such as demolition

                  methodologies and the quality of brick itself. Brick recycling into aggregate has been happening for decades but does their true
                  value lie elsewhere?
                  Research has shown that this material can be substituted into creating the ingredients for products such as low carbon concrete

                  multiplying the number of practical uses. Sometimes it is easy to over complicate material reuse therefore the opportunity to
                  reuse bricks in a new developments should never be overlooked.



                 Bricks can potentially be recovered and reused, but most often they are crushed and recycled into fill materials or recycled aggregate. Although there is a market for
                 recovered clay bricks, it is not always done, commonly due to the inability to remove mortar from the bricks.

                 Traditional lime-based mortars are generally weaker than cement-based mortars and hence easier to remove. The more recent use of strong mortars with a high cement

                 content can
                 increase the time and effort required to remove the mortar and/ or lead to subsequent damage to the bricks. These mortars may be chosen to improve longevity in use and
                 reduce maintenance requirements from repointing for
                 instance.

                 It is recommended that bricks that are unable to be reused are segregated either onsite or at a waste facility and
                 crushed to produce recycled aggregate (RA).

                 Bricks can also be reused through Brick Salvage companies. There has also been interesting developments in Brick reuse research into turning bricks into aggregates for new
                 concrete, something John F Hunt has assisted with in order to broaden the market for brick reuse.


                  Potential Waste Management Routes


                  Option 1 – Material removed from structure and then recycled off site into new aggregates (RA)
                  Option 2 – Invite a Brick Reclamation Company to collect from John F Hunt
                  Option 3 – Reuse within new development
                                                                                                                                                         32]]></page><page Index="33"><![CDATA[Bricks – John F Hunt Case Study





              Brick Valorisation – Brunel University


               John F Hunt has been working in partnership with Brunel University to study the potential of
               Brick Valorisation and its applications in the construction industry. Through taking bricks
               that would otherwise be recycled or taken to landfill and using state of the art techniques
               to reconstitute the brick into an aggregate to be used for concrete mixes. Concrete
               manufacture is linked to vast amount of CO2 emissions, stemming from the ash mixes
               used, any ready to use replacement for Fly Ash mixes will vastly reduce the embodied
               Carbon in concrete products. Along with replacing damaging Fly Ash, Brick aggregate
               will be used as an alternative to the finite natural resource of natural sand usually taking
               from river beds.



                                                                                         The material itself will not be reused as Brick blocks but instead will constitute part of the recipe

                                                                                         for low carbon concrete. The diagram above shows the breakdown of the potential recipe mix
                                                                                         for Low Carbon Concrete. The Brick Powder (0-125 microns) replaces the CO2 laden Fly Ash,
                                                                                         and the recycled Brick aggregate replaces the natural sand.
                                                                                         There are many potential applications of using Brick Valorisation techniques both structural and
                                                                                         non-structural. Structurally speaking this product could be used for a for concrete slabs in future
                                                                                         once approved by accreditation providers.

                                                                                         Non-structurally, which may be of interest to John F Hunt sooner, could have many
                                                                                         applications. Mass concrete options such as Non-Structural Plinths and backfilling are options
                                                                                         that could be used on sites. Concrete foundations for low level temporary buildings such as
                         John F Hunt has donated bricks from our Cundy Street Quarter    Welfare and Site Offices in the future, as well as hard standing areas for plant and material

                                Project to assist in Brick Valorisation Research         storage. For any site in an urban area Kentledge blocks are needed for hoarding construction,
                                                                                         therefore a huge application of this method of concrete manufactory would be Kentledge
                                                                                         blocks, which John F Hunt is actively looking at supplying.


                                                                                                                                                         33]]></page><page Index="34"><![CDATA[Bricks Waste Procedure






















































                                                                                                                                                         34]]></page><page Index="35"><![CDATA[Circular Economy Guide


    Timber


























                                                                                                                                                         35]]></page><page Index="36"><![CDATA[Timber





                  Material Summary
                  Timber is one of the most used materials on construction sites and yet much of the timber being used on projects is single use to the point of
                  recycling. In order to maximise the life cycle potential of timber all options must be investigated before traditional recycling is opted for.

                  John F Hunt are constantly on the search for new and innovative ways that timber can not only be recycled into new products but to be
                  reused in its original form.

                  Timber procurement is limited on John F Hunt projects due to the nature of works occurring, but all timber is FSC certified with the company
                  looking at other ways to limit single use procurement through products such as Eco Hoarding.



                 Timber is one of the most versatile materials with a construction project. If offers the ability to recycle easily but also be reused on the initial
                 project or off site.

                 Products within the project that are composed of timber should be segregated and then reused. Materials such as doors and fittings can
                 be offered on Reuse platforms such as Globechain. Items that need to be broken down or damaged to remove can be given to partners,
                 such as Community Wood Recycling, to save them from direct recycle. This also means materials coming off site have a positive social
                 aspect.

                 Recycling timber is now a bare minimum throughout any project. Material can be broken down on site and then sent to a contacted
                 waste carrier. If reuse is not viable, most of the solid timber can be recycled, usually into chipboard. Guidance has been issued for
                 consideration of potentially hazardous treatments. Timber should be segregated on site, if space permits, to improve level of reuse or
                 recycling. If sent offsite to a licensed waste management contractor, this will typically result in recycling for chipboard (if well segregated)
                 or as an energy feedstock (especially when mixed with other materials).




                  Potential Waste Management Routes



                  Option 1 – Material removed from structure and then recycled off site into new products

                  Option 2 – Use a Reuse platform or timber reclamation programmes to remove and reuse material

                  Option 3 – Reuse within new development
                                                                                                                                                         36]]></page><page Index="37"><![CDATA[Timber – John F Hunt Case Studies




                     Timber Reuse – Oasis Charity Building Reuse

        Oasis is a charity founded in 1973 that provides diverse educational play space for young people in Stockwell.
        The projects that Oasis provides are open access and available for local children, including children with
        disabilities and complex needs to attend after school, on Saturdays and during the school holidays.

        OasisPlay is managed by a voluntary management committee funded by the London Borough of Lambeth,
        The Big Lottery, BBC Children In Need, The Walcot Foundation and Comic Relief.
        Through working with Marks Barfield Architects to rebuild a facility for their ‘nature garden’ as it is no longer fit
        for purpose. The new building will incorporate an additional classroom, office space and a forest nursery school
        as well as enhancing the biodiversity for the nature garden itself. They are currently looking at reducing their
        carbon footprint during the build as much as possible, starting with re-used materials.

        At our 1 Exchange Square project there were two timber framed out buildings that were previously used for
        entertainment spaces. John F Hunt carefully dismantled the outbuildings so they could be used again for the
        Oasis charity. This has not only given the materials a new lease of life but enabled them to be used in an
        entirely new way.

                                                                                                             Source: Communitywoodrecycling.org.uk (Moving Towards a Circular Economy)


                                                                                                                Community Wood Recycling

                                                                                                 John F Hunt has partnered with Community Wood Recycling to not only reduce
                                                                                                 Timber waste in the industry but also provide opportunities for local communities up
                                                                                                 and down the country.

                                                                                                 Community Wood Recycling offers an ideal home for unused or wasted timber as not
                                                                                                 only does the organisation reuse the material but also trains local people in skills such

                                                                                                 as carpentry. They regularly train up to 600 people a year in life changing skills offering
                                                                                                 a pathway into careers for their apprentices.
                                                                                                 John F Hunt has supplied over 40 tonnes of timber to these projects with a saving to
                                                                                                 the trainings programme of over £7000.


                                                                                                                                                         37]]></page><page Index="38"><![CDATA[Timber Waste Procedure





















































                                                                                                                                                         38]]></page><page Index="39"><![CDATA[Timber Procurement Procedure






















































                                                                                                                                                         39]]></page><page Index="40"><![CDATA[Circular Economy Guide


    Glass


























                                                                                                                                                         40]]></page><page Index="41"><![CDATA[Glass





                  Material Summary
                  Glass is 100% recyclable and through its properties can be recycled endlessly without loss of quality.  Recycled glass can save up
                  to 1.2 tonnes of raw material per tonne of recycled glass- creating a real demand for glass leaving demolition projects. Each

                  time one tonne of glass is recycled, about 580kg CO2 is saved throughout the supply chain, air pollution is reduced by 20% and
                  water pollution cut by 50%.

                  Recycling glass is a great step in the right direction but if glass can reused in its current form it will not only save on the Co2
                  needed for production but create opportunities for reuse in new developments.



                 Glass can be collected in skips and containers for recycling. The quality of the glass in the skips will be dependent upon the
                 awareness and training of those working on site and appropriate site management is required along with clear signage. They also
                 need to be close to the workplace due health and safety risks from transporting glass.

                 One of the limiting factors in the use of post-consumer flat glass as cullet back into the float glass manufacturing process is the
                 availability of it in the right quality and chemical compatibility as the manufacturing process is sensitive to low levels of
                 contamination. Most of post-consumer flat glass waste produced does not go back into glass and will be used as aggregate or
                 landfilled. For demolition, it is more likely to be crushed into aggregate with other inert waste.  For glass to be reused it needs to
                 be collected on specialist steel A frame stillages, handled and stored carefully.

                 There is potential for glass to be reused in the redevelopment, but this would need to be considered in light of possible end uses/
                 users, alongside the H&S and cost implications of extracting without damage.




                  Potential Waste Management Routes



                  Option 1 – Material removed from structure and then recycled off site into new products
                  Option 2 – Use a ReUse platform to remove and reuse material
                  Option 3 – ReUse within new development for areas such as internal glass partitions
                                                                                                                                                         41]]></page><page Index="42"><![CDATA[Glass Reuse – John F Hunt Case Studies






            Window Reuse Investigation – Cundy Street Quarter



           Through discussions with Architecture firm Morris + Company we were able to identify the
           potential reuse of Sash windows at our Cundy Street Quarter project. Throughout the four
           apartment complexes on the site we identified over 120 suitable Sash windows for reuse in a
           variety of different options.

           These options ranged from new greenhouse facilities for community gardens or internal
           partitions used in office spaces throughout London. Through the early identification of these
           possibilities it becomes possible to use materials in ways that were previously unthought of.
           Discussions within the design stage of a project makes these schemes possible and is not only
           something that applies to glass as a material but all materials found on projects.









                                                                   Globechain – Glass Reuse

                                                    In working with our reuse partner Globechain we have been able to donate glass to various
                                                    different charities and businesses within the local area. This has removed the need for glass
                                                    recycling and offered much needed materials for the end users.
                                                    At our 1 Exchange Square project we have donated multiple decorative glass panels to
                                                    local charities who are using them in their office spaces. Globechain offers us the chance to
                                                    not only donate materials but also to have a detailed chain of custody so we are confident
                                                    that all material is being reused in appropriate ways.





                                                                                                                                                         42]]></page><page Index="43"><![CDATA[Glass Waste Procedure





















































                                                                                                                                                         43]]></page><page Index="44"><![CDATA[Circular Economy Guide


    Furniture & Materials























                                                                                                                                                         44]]></page><page Index="45"><![CDATA[Furniture/Internal Materials






                  Material Summary
                  The idea of buildings as materials banks has been discussed for some time now and no greater example of this can be found in
                  the internal fixtures and fittings of the structure itself. Through early engagement of client, contractors and stakeholders internal

                  materials can be identified and segregated optimising the chance for reuse in other projects.

                  Opportunities for reuse are abundant in internal materials and offer the chance to not only save on Co2 related to production
                  chains for new materials but giving materials a new lease of life.



                    Internal materials that are removed during the soft strip phase of demolition provide a great opportunity to increase
                 recycling rates and if possible to be reused by partners on future projects.                             Internal items are collected and
                                                                                                                                   segregated
                 Plasterboard items can be removed and recycled. Plasterboard recycling rates vary due to the materials within the
                 product. Plasterboard products are often shredded and then reconstituted as new plasterboard products. In some
                 cases plasterboard needs to be crushed with other materials producing mixed recycling aggregates.

                 Metal products such as RAF and Ceiling tiles can be easily recycled, but have a huge potential to be reused. RAF
                 and ceiling tiles will be taken out and separated, they can then be offered to Reuse platforms.
                                                                                                                   Internal items are          Internal items that
                 Carpet tiles can be recycled using traditional recycling methods. Items that are in good condition can be stored and   offered on Reuse   cannot be reused will
                 reused using reuse platforms.
                                                                                                                platforms and reused           be recycled off site
                 Any other materials that are within the building will be analysed and the waste management route will be      in future projects
                 determined based on difficulty and programme implications.


                   Potential Waste Management Routes                                                                                           Shredded materials
                                                                                                                                               will be reconstituted
                   Option 1 – Material removed from structure and then recycled off site into new products                                      into new products
                   Option 2 – Use a Reuse platform to remove and reuse material

                   Option 3 – Reuse within new development
                                                                                                                                                         45]]></page><page Index="46"><![CDATA[Furniture/Internal Materials – John F Hunt Case Studies






              Materials Reuse Partner - Globechain

             Globechain is a data-centric reuse marketplace, connecting enterprises with over
             10,000 non-profits, small businesses and people to redistribute unneeded items,
             generating ESG data on the impact. The full reporting tools ensure visibility and
             transparency with Reuse data.
             Anything can be listed for reuse, from furniture and equipment to construction and
             bulk materials. We can specify when items need to be collected by minimising
             stockpiling on site. Through partnering with Globechain, we can manage our
             waste, calculate carbon emissions and optimise our BREEAM performance.
             Socially, we will be helping local communities in line with the UN Climate Change
             targets and the Social Value Act 2012.


             Our experience using Globechain:
             We used onsite at the Cundy Street Quarter demolition project in Westminster,
             during which 4No. residential blocks will be demolished. Since commencement on
             site, we have successfully diverted 19,644kg of surplus items from landfill. Since
             starting on site, we have listed 1,021 items via Globechain, 931 of which have
             been reclaimed and collected. These items have directly benefitted 600 people
             and saved them £21,841.40.
             We have also partnered with Globechain at 1 Liverpool St, 20 Manchester Sq, and
             Euston Tower.






                                                                                                                                                         46]]></page><page Index="47"><![CDATA[Furniture/Internal Materials – John F Hunt Case Studies





                                                                                                Raised Access Flooring and Carpet Tile Reuse


                                                                                             Through early engagement with Reuse partners John F Hunt has, on several projects,
                                                                                             successfully reused carpet tiles and raised access flooring.
                                                                                             Carpet tiles throughout projects can easily be reused if they are in good condition
                                                                                             with suppliers purchasing carpet tiles to be reused in new office areas.
                                                                                             Raised access flooring is a product that was once added to mixed metal recycling
                                                                                             but due to its ability to be dismantled easily it can segregated and stored for future
                                                                                             reuse either on the new development or through external partners.
                                                                                             In partnering the Raised Access Flooring Supplies we have supplied the reuse market
                                                                                             with over 56,000 RAF tiles. At our 1 Exchange Square project we have reused 53841
                                                                                             tiles, offering a saving of 590 tonnes of steel that would have to be manufactured.

                                                                                             John F Hunt are committed to reusing these materials were possible and have
                                                                                             established networks to ensure items are diverted from waste facilities in the future.















                                                                                                                                                         47]]></page><page Index="48"><![CDATA[Furniture & Materials Waste Procedure




















































                                                                                                                                                         48]]></page><page Index="49"><![CDATA[Circular Economy


    Fuels































                                                                                                                                                         49]]></page><page Index="50"><![CDATA[HVO Fuels




                  Material Summary

                  Hydrotreated Vegetable Oil (HVO) is a type of renewable diesel fuel produced through a hydrotreating process. It is derived from
                  feedstocks such as vegetable oils, animal fats, and used cooking oils, which are subjected to a hydrogenation process to remove
                  impurities and reduce the level of oxygen content. The result is a clear and colourless liquid with properties very similar to conventional
                  fossil diesel fuel.
                  When HVO is used as a fuel, it typically emits lower levels of carbon dioxide (CO2) and other greenhouse gases compared to
                  conventional fossil fuels like petroleum-based diesel.






                 John F Hunt is committed to reducing it’s Carbon Footprint wherever the opportunity arises. As well
                 as the construction based products we procure fuels take up a large part of materials bought.
                 Larger projects often require specialised pieces of plant that consume large quantities of fuel to
                 sustain themselves. In the past this has led to carbon emissions with little opportunity to rectify the
                 issue due to fuel technology and the models of the plant themselves.
                 Innovation within the fuel industry has led to the widespread availability of HVO fuels. HVO stands for
                 Hydrotreated Vegetable Oil and is created by hydrogenation of vegetable oils to create molecules
                 that are similar within traditional fuels such as kerosene or gasoline.
                 The fuel itself offers up to a 90% reduction in Co2 emissions, a 30% reduction in NOx emissions and up
                 to 86% reduction in particulate matter.
                 As of July 2023 John F Hunt has purchased over 350,000 litres of HVO fuel clearly outline our intention
                 to use greener methods of combustion in the future.






                                                                                                                                                         50]]></page><page Index="51"><![CDATA[HVO – Procurement Procedure





















































                                                                                                                                                         51]]></page><page Index="52"><![CDATA[HVO – John F Hunt Case Study






                 Cundy Street Quarter                                                                        Co2e(T)



                 John F Hunt have used HVO fuel at our Cundy Street project
                 in line with our client’s own carbon reduction goals.
                 Throughout the project 4,200 litres of HVO fuel were       Traditional Diesel Fuel                                            11.59
                 purchased and used on plant conducting the demolition of
                 4 tower blocks.
                 Through using HVO fuels on the projects John F Hunt have
                 managed to save 11.44 tonnes of Co2(e) that would have
                 emitted using traditional fuels.

                                                                               John F Hunt HVO    0.15



                     4200                                                                      0       2       4       6       8       10      12      14






                  Litres of HVO Used


                                              11.44t






                                              Co2e Saved


                                                                                                                                                         52]]></page><page Index="53"><![CDATA[Circular Economy Partnerships


    Database






















                                                                                                                                                         53]]></page><page Index="54"><![CDATA[Circular Partnerships Database



                                                                            SITE INVESTIGATIONS
                 Company name             Location            Service/product description                           Website/contact
                 Fugro                    Wallingford, UK     Materials testing and structural investigations       http://www.fugro.com/our-services/land-site-
                                                                                                                    characterisation/testing-
                                                                                                                    monitoring/construction-materials-engineering-
                                                                                                                    and-testing
                 CBG                      Cambridgeshire, UK   Materials testing and structural investigations      http://www.gbg.co.uk/structural-investigation
                 Sandberg                 London, UK          Materials testing and structural investigations       http://www.sandberg.co.uk/


                                                                     MATERIAL REUSE STOCKISTS / SUPPLIERS
                 Company name             Location            Service/product description                           Website/contact
                 Ainscough Metals         Lancashire, UK      Steel reuse                                           http://www.ainscoughmetals.co.uk/
                 Bruggenbank – second hand   The Netherlands   As major clients for infrastructure projects, the cities of Amsterdam   http://www.nationalebruggenbank.nl/en/
                 bridges                                      and Rotterdam have joined forces to establish an independent
                                                              platform for reusing bridges
                                                              and bridge components.
                 Cleveland Steel & Tubes   Yorkshire, UK      Steel reuse                                           http://www.cleveland-steel.com/
                 CollectEco               Bristol, UK         Furnitures/fixtures collection service for third sector   http://www.collecteco.co.uk/
                 Community Wood Recycling   UK-wide           Wood – waste from construction / demolition as well as from   http://www.communitywoodrecycling.org.uk/
                                                              timber mills, joinery shops and other wood product manufacturing
                 EMR                      Warrington, UK      Steel reuse                                           http://www.uk.emrgroup.com/
                 Enfield Excess Materials   Essex, UK         Construction materials including steelwork, bricks, cladding,   http://www.enfield.excessmaterialsexchange.co
                 Exchange                                     aggregates salvaged from Meridian Water project       m/
                 Enviromate               UK, US, Australia,   Leftover building materials – wide range from timber, rubble,   http://www.enviromate.co.uk/
                                          Europe              doors, stairs, insulation
                 Excess Materials Exchange   Based in Amsterdam –   Any material, component or (waste) product can be exchanged   http://www.excessmaterialsexchange.com/nl/
                                          transport can be    on EME’s digital platform
                                          organised to other
                                          European cities
                 Globechain               London, UK          Construction materials marketplace                    http://www.globechain.com/
                 Material Reuse Portal    London, UK          One of five platforms built for the CIRCuIT project. It brings   https://www.materialreuseportal.com/
                                                              together construction materials from multiple
                                                              marketplaces to create a single place where reuseable materials
                                                              can be found.


                                                                                                                                                         54]]></page><page Index="55"><![CDATA[Opalis (run by Rotor)    UK                  Resellers of: landscaping and paving, cobble stone and pavers,   http://www.opalis.co.uk/en
                                                              floors in natural stone, structure
                                                              and shell, timber framing, steps in stone, steel structure, bricks,
                                                              insulation, slates, roof tiles and wall
                                                              covers, cladding, woodwork, windows, doors, stairs, interior
                                                              finishings, floors in natural stone, parquet
                                                              and wooden floors, tiles, partitions and suspended ceilings,
                                                              cladding, equipment, sanitary, technical
                                                              installations, radiators, lights, decoration, architectural antiques,
                                                              metal work, chimneys
                 Oxford Wood Recycling    Oxford, UK          Timber reuse and recycling                            http://www.oxfordwoodrecycling.org.uk/
                 Salvoweb                 UK, France, Germany,   Architectural antiques, decorative antiques and furniture,   http://www.salvoweb.com/
                                          US, Australia       architectural salvage, garden antiques, rural
                                                              domestic industrial and institutional bygones, reclaimed building
                                                              materials and demolition salvage.


                                                                       STRUCTURAL CIRCULAR PRODUCTS
                 Company name             Location            Service/product description                           Website/contact
                 Façade Click             Belgium             Brick façade click system                             http://www.facadeclick.be/
                 K-Briq                   Edinburgh, UK       Brick made out of 90% demolition waste                http://www.kenoteq.com/
                 Lindapter                Bradford, UK        Demountable steel connections                         http://www.lindapter.com/


                                                                     ARCHITECTURAL CIRCULAR PRODUCTS
                 Company name             Location            Service/product description                           Website/contact
                 AltRock                  London, UK          Upcycled terrazzo floors                              http://www.altrocksurfaces.com/
                 Autex                    NZ with UK Offices   Acoustic products with ranges made from recycled plastic fibres   http://www.autexglobal.com/
                 Baux                     Sweden              Biobased acoustic products                            http://www.baux.com/acoustic-products/wood-
                                                                                                                    wool/panels/
                 Crown Workspace          London, UK          Refurbished office furniture supplier                 http://www.crownworkspace.com/uk/
                 Fagerhult                Europe              Circular lighting                                     http://www.fagerhult.com/about-
                                                                                                                    fagerhult/sustainability/circular-solutions/
                 Foresso                  Birmingham, UK      Timber terrazzo                                       http://www.foresso.co.uk/
                 GoodWaste                London, UK          Furniture from waste materials                        http://www.goodwaste.net/
                 Grohe                    Germany with UK     Brassware with Cradle to Cradle certified range       http://www.grohe.co.uk/en_gb/our-
                                          offices                                                                   service/about-grohe/sustainability/
                 Honext                   Spain               Biobased board for interiors                          http://www.honexmaterial.com/
                 Interface                Global              Carpet tiles with high recycled content, adhesive-free options,   http://www.interface.com/GB/en-GB?r=1
                                                              take back scheme
                 Mosa Façade Systems      Global              Ceramic façade cladding (Cradle to Cradle certified)   http://www.mosa.com/en


                                                                                                                                                         55]]></page><page Index="56"><![CDATA[Optima                   High Wycombe, UK    Reuse of glass partitions and doors                   http://www.optimasystems.com/reuse-service-
                                                                                                                    glass-partitions/
                 Orluna                   Worldwide           Lighting products with 20-year repair and reuse guarantee   http://www.orluna.com/circular-product
                 Paint 360                Halesowen, UK       Reclaimed & recycled paint                            http://www.paint360.co.uk/
                 Parkside Tiles           London, Leicester, UK   Tiles with high recycled content and alternative manufacturing   http://www.parkside.co.uk/
                                                              techniques to lower carbon footprint
                 RMF                      Leamington Spa, UK   Raised floor systems                                 http://www.rmf-services.co.uk/
                 Stone Cycling            The Netherlands     Brick with high recycled content                      http://www.stonecycling.com/
                 Tarkett                  Global              Carpet tiles with C2C range                           http://www.commercial.tarkett.com/products/c
                                                                                                                    arpet/carpet-tiles-planks
                 TRACO UK                 Portsmouth, UK      Reused office equipment and furniture                 http://www.recycledassets.co.uk/
                 Whitecroft Lighting      Ashton-under-Lyne, UK   Vitality: refurbish, repurpose, redistribute, resell and in the end   http://www.whitecroftlighting.com/products/whi
                                                              recover luminaires                                    tecroft-vitality-circular-products/
                 Wicona                   Global              Aluminium curtain walling                             http://www.wicona.com/en/int




                                                                                  OTHER
                 Company name             Location            Service/product description                           Website/contact
                 Building Deconstruction   USA                Deconstruction and reuse of timber buildings          http://www.reuseconsulting.com/deconstruction
                 Institute                                                                                          -institute-1
                 Cradle to Cradle product   The Netherlands   All C2C products list                                 http://www.c2ccertified.org/
                 registry
                 Grosvenor/UKGBC reuse    UK                  Network for material exchange                         http://www.grosvenor.com/materialreuse
                 network
                 Unbuilders               Canada              Deconstruction and upcycling of timber buildings      http://www.unibuilders.com/




















                                                                                                                                                         56]]></page><page Index="57"><![CDATA[Low Carbon Supplier Database





                                                                                   STEEL
                 Company name        Location         Service/product description              Pricing                      Website/contact
                 Celsa Steel UK      Cardiff          Low carbon rebar supplier                TBC                          https://www.celsauk.com/
                 ROM                 UK               Low carbon rebar supplier                ~ £770 / tonnes              https://www.rom.co.uk/
                 ArcelorMittal       Spain            Low carbon steel supplier                TBC                          https://corporate.arcelormittal.com/
                                                                                                                            climate-action/xcarb
                 British Steel       UK               Low carbon steel supplier                TBC                          https://britishsteel.co.uk/
                 Tata Steel          UK               Low carbon steel supplier                TBC                          https://www.tatasteeleurope.com/
                 Heyne Tillet Steel   UK              Low carbon structural steel civil engineers   TBC                     https://hts.uk.com/


                                                                                 CONCRETE
                 Company name        Location         Service/product description              Pricing                      Website/contact
                 Tarmac              UK               Low carbon concrete supplier             TBC                          https://tarmac.com/low-carbon-
                                                                                                                            concrete/
                 Cemex               UK               Low carbon concrete supplier             TBC                          https://www.cemex.co.uk/lower-
                                                                                                                            carbon-concrete
                 Hanson              UK               Low carbon concrete supplier             TBC                          https://www.hanson.co.uk/en/hanson-
                                                                                                                            location-finder



                                                                                  TIMBER
                 Company name        Location         Service/product description              Pricing                      Website/contact
                 South London Timber   London, UK     FSC Timber                               TBC                          https://sltimber.co.uk/product/fsc-
                                                                                                                            plywood/
                 Eco Choice          Cambridge, UK    FSC & Sustainable Timber                 TBC                          https://ecochoice.co.uk/products







                                                                                                                                                         57]]></page><page Index="58"><![CDATA[Environmental Product Declaration (EPD) Database





                                                                                   STEEL
                 Company name     Product description          Registration Number   EPD Expiry Date   Embodied Carbon   Source
                                                                                                     (Global Warming
                                                                                                     Potential – GWP)
                 Celsa Steel UK   Hot rolled wire rod and reinforcing   S-P-07496   23/11/2027       429 kgCo2 / Tonne   S-P-07496 - Hot rolled wire rod and
                                  steel products                                                                        reinforcing steel products
                                                                                                                        (environdec.com)
                 Celsa Steel UK   Hot rolled wire rod and reinforcing   S-P-07498   23/11/2027       324 kgCo2 / Tonne   S-P-07498 - Hot rolled wire rod and
                                  steel products. (100% Renewable                                                       reinforcing steel products. (100%
                                  Electricity)                                                                          Renewable Electricity) (environdec.com)
                 Hy-Ten           Fabricated steel reinforcement   S-P-02388      23/01/2024         779.1 kgCo2 / Tonne   S-P-02388 - Fabricated steel reinforcement
                                  products (cut and bent rebar)                                                         products (cut and bent rebar)
                                                                                                                        (environdec.com)
                 Midland Steel    Rolled steel production      1340               n/a                807 kgCO2 / Tonne   CC11746BK Midland Steel Reinforcement
                 Reinforcement                                                                                          Supplies Mountmellic _CFR 2020.pdf



                                                                                 CONCRETE
                 Company name     Product description          Registration Number   EPD Expiry Date   Embodied Carbon   Source
                                                                                                     (Global Warming
                                                                                                     Potential – GWP)
                 General – Mineral   UK Average Portland Cement   EPD-MPA-20170159-  13/11/2022 (For   830 kgCo2e / Tonne   EPD - Tarmac
                 Products         (CEM1)                       CAG1-EN            reference only)
                 Association (MPA)
                 /                Unreinforced, C30/37, UK average    /           /                  103                MPA, 2018 [2]
                                  ready-mixed concrete EPD[1] (35%
                                  cement
                                  replacement)
                 /                Unreinforced, C32/40, 25% GGBS    /             /                  120                ICE V3 [4]
                                  cement replacement[3]
                 /                Unreinforced, C32/40, 50% GGBS    /             /                  89                 ICE V3
                                  cement replacement
                 /                Unreinforced, C32/40, 75% GGBS    /             /                  63                 ICE V3


                                                                                                                                                         58]]></page><page Index="59"><![CDATA[cement replacement
                 /                Unreinforced, C40/50, 25% GGBS    /             /                  138                ICE V3
                                  cement replacement
                 /                Unreinforced, C40/50, 50% GGBS    /             /                  102                ICE V3
                                  cement replacement
                 /                Unreinforced, C40/50, 75% GGBS    /             /                  72                 ICE V3
                                  cement replacement















































                                                                                                                                                         59]]></page><page Index="60"><![CDATA[Looking Forward



    2023 onwards





























                                                                                                                                                         60]]></page><page Index="61"><![CDATA[Innovation





               Hydrogen

               Hydrogen Fuel Cells for Power Generation: Hydrogen fuel cells can be utilized on construction sites to provide clean and reliable power for tools,
               equipment, and temporary site offices. Fuel cells generate electricity through a chemical reaction between hydrogen and oxygen, with water
               vapor being the only emission, making them an eco-friendly alternative to traditional diesel generators.

               Hydrogen for Steel Production: The construction industry relies heavily on steel, which is traditionally produced using coal-based methods.
               Hydrogen can act as a clean alternative to reduce iron ore and produce "green steel." This method avoids carbon dioxide emissions and can
               significantly lower the carbon footprint of construction materials.

               Hydrogen-Powered Construction Vehicles: Hydrogen fuel cell and ICE technology is being explored for construction equipment like excavators,
               cranes, and trucks. These vehicles can operate with lower noise levels and zero harmful emissions, making them ideal for reducing pollution in
               urban construction areas.


               Low Carbon Concrete

               Low Carbon Concrete: Innovations in concrete production involve using low carbon or alternative cementitious materials to reduce the carbon
               footprint of concrete. This includes using supplementary cementitious materials like fly ash, slag, and silica fume, as well as exploring carbon
               capture and utilization (CCU) technologies.


               Battery Storage

               Energy Efficiency and Demand Management: Battery storage systems enable construction sites to store excess energy generated during periods
               of low demand or high renewable energy production. This stored energy can then be used during peak demand times, reducing the need to
               draw power from the grid and optimizing energy consumption.

               Renewable Energy Integration: Construction sites with renewable energy sources, such as solar panels or wind turbines, can utilize battery

                                                                                                                                                         61]]></page><page Index="62"><![CDATA[storage to store surplus energy when generation exceeds demand. The stored energy can be used later, including during non-productive hours,
               to offset the need for conventional grid electricity.

               Demand Response and Load Shifting: Battery storage allows construction companies to participate in demand response programs, where they
               can adjust their energy consumption based on grid demand and pricing signals. This not only helps stabilize the grid but can also result in cost
               savings for construction site operators.


               Circular Economy

               Materials Reuse and Salvage: Instead of demolishing buildings and sending materials to landfills, circular construction seeks to deconstruct
               buildings carefully to salvage and reuse materials like bricks, wood, metal, and glass. These materials can be incorporated into new projects or
               sold for reuse.

               Design for Disassembly (DfD): Implementing DfD principles ensures that buildings are designed with future disassembly and material recovery in
               mind. Components can be easily dismantled and reused or recycled when the building reaches the end of its life.

               Circular Business Models: Construction companies are exploring circular business models that emphasize product-as-a-service offerings. Rather
               than selling building materials, companies may lease or lend products, ensuring their recovery and reuse at the end of their life.

               Circular Supply Chains: Encouraging circularity throughout the supply chain involves collaborating with suppliers to source materials responsibly,
               increase recycling rates, and promote sustainable practices.

               BIM


               Construction BIM (Building Information Modelling) innovation involves the continuous improvement and development of BIM technologies and
               practices to enhance the construction process, improve collaboration, and optimize project outcomes.

               Generative Design in BIM: Generative design algorithms use BIM data to explore and generate multiple design alternatives based on specified
               parameters, fostering innovative and optimized design solutions.

               BIM for Sustainable Construction: BIM is utilized to assess and optimize the environmental impact of buildings, helping designers make informed
               decisions to create more sustainable structures.





                                                                                                                                                         62]]></page><page Index="63"><![CDATA[Buildings as materials banks (BAMB)


               Design for Disassembly (DfD): Buildings are designed with DfD principles, considering the ease of deconstruction and the recovery of valuable
               materials. Components are carefully chosen and assembled so that they can be easily separated and reused or recycled when the building
               reaches the end of its life.

               Material Passports: Material passports are created for buildings, containing detailed information about the origin, composition, and quality of
               the materials used. This data is stored digitally and allows for easy identification and traceability of materials, facilitating their future recovery
               and reuse.

               Selective Demolition: When a building reaches the end of its life or requires renovation, selective demolition techniques are employed to
               carefully deconstruct and disassemble the building. This involves salvaging and segregating reusable materials for future use.




































                                                                                                                                                         63]]></page></pages></Search>